Register of the Donald Marquand Dozer Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- PANAMA CANAL FILE, 1901-1980
  - Interest groups
    - Citizens groups - General
      - Council for Inter-American Security, 1976-1980
        - General. Annual report, form letters, memorandum, pamphlets, flyers, letter to Rep. Daniel Flood. (Folder 7)
        - Newsletters (West Watch) (Folder 8)
      - Council of the Americas, Letter and pamphlet, United States, Panama and the Panama Canal: A Guide to the Issues, circa 1977. (Folder 9)
      - Daughters of the American Revolution, Newsletters, resolutions, flyer, correspondence with ECSCZ, 1966-1977. (Folder 10)
      - Defenders of the American Constitution, Bulletins, newsletter (Task Force), letters to ECSCZ, Congress, and others, 1965-1977. (Folder 11)
      - Heritage Foundation, Clippings, newsletter and reports entitled "The Canal Zone--Panama and the U.S.," "Panama: The Terms of the Treaties" and "The Economic Implications of the Panama Canal Treaties", 1975-1978. (Folder 12)
      - Institute of American Relations, Flyer and newsletters, 1978-1980. (Folder 13)
      - Liberty Lobby, 1966-1978
        - General. Flyer, statements, press releases, newsletters (Liberty Letter), correspondence with ECSCZ (Folder 14)
        - Serial issues (National Spotlight) (Folder 15-17)
      - Sons of the American Revolution. Form letters, correspondence and resolutions, including draft by Dr. Dozer, 1972-1978 (Box 66, Folder 1)
      - Women for Constitutional Government, Flyer and newsletter, 1975. (Folder 2)
    - Citizens groups - Political organizations (primarily California Republicans)
      - General, Press release, newsletters, form letters, resolutions, correspondence with Dr. Dozer, letters to Ronald Reagan and George Meany, 1967-1977. (Folder 3)
      - Reagan, Ronald
        - General, Clippings (primarily Mr. Reagan's newspaper column), media broadcasts, campaign material, speech transcripts. Includes statement from unidentified Republican objecting to one of Mr. Reagan's statements. Note: for other correspondence, SEE: ECSCZ/ Correspondence/ Reagan, Ronald, 1975-1978. (Folder 4)
        - Newsletters, Citizens for the Republic, Also includes form letter, 1977-1979. (Folder 5)
    - Citizens groups - Specific canal committees
      - General. (Miscellaneous groups, predominantly, but not necessarily anti-treaty). Flyers, pamphlet, letter to Dr. Dozer, newsletters, form letters, newspaper clippings and advertisements, 1974-1979 (Folder 6)
      - American Emergency Committee on the Panama Canal. Pamphlet, press release, form letters and memoranda, correspondence with ECSCZ, 1967-1968 (Folder 7)
      - Emergency Committee to Save the U.S. Canal Zone (Donald Dozer, William Collier, Miles DuVal, primary activists)
        - General
          - General. Biographical material, business cards, schedules, radio transcript, address lists, stationery, and bank statement, 1972-1977 (Folder 8)
          - Isthmian Canal College. Correspondence with the IRS, by-laws, form letter, notes (Folder 9)
        - Correspondence. NOTE: Only the most significant correspondence of the ECSCZ has been listed here. Much has been integrated with other groups; for example, correspondence with the American Legion will be found with the other Legion materials.
          - General
            - General
              - General. Unidentified correspondents (Folder 10)
              - Internal correspondence
                - undated-1967 (Folder 11-14)
                - 1968-1980 (Box 67, Folder 1-11)
            - Business groups, Includes Panama Canal Pilots Association and the American Federation of Government Employees (Stephen A. Koczak), 1968-1974. (Box 68, Folder 1)
            - Citizen's and public policy organizations, Includes a variety of enclosures of non-printed and printed materials. Arranged alphabetically, 1964-1978. (Folder 2-9)
            - Media, 1967-1978 (Folder 10)
            - U.S. Congress
              - General. Form letter, fragments and holographs to individuals not otherwise itemized (Folder 11)
              - Alexander, William V., 1975-1977 (Folder 12)
              - Allen, James B., 1976-1977
              - Ashbrook, John, 1972-1974
              - Byrd, Harry F., Jr., 1975-1977
              - Cotton, Norris, Includes typescript report by W. Collier, 1973.
              - Crane, Philip, 1973
              - Dominick, Peter H., 1971
              - Flood, Daniel J., 1966-1978
              - Goldwater, Barry, Jr., 1973
              - Gross, H.R., Includes typescript report by Dr. Dozer, 1967-1973.
              - Hall, Durward, 1969
              - Hansen, George, 1977-1979
              - Hayakawa, S.I., Holograph and telegram, 1977-1978.
              - Helms, Jesse, Includes correspondence with James Lucier, aide to Senator Helms, 1973-1978.
              - Lagomarsino, Robert J., 1975-1977 (Folder 13)
              - Laxalt, Paul, 1978
              - McClellan, John L., 1975
              - McDonald, Lawrence, 1977
              - Murphy, George, 1966-1978
              - Rarick, John R., 1967-1973
              - Sarbanes, Paul S., 1978
              - Snyder, Gene, Holograph and typescript, 1975-1977.
              - Sullivan, Lenore, 1969-1973
              - Teague, Charles M., 1967-1973
              - Thurmond, Strom, 1969-1972
              - Tower, John, 1966-1972
          - Batt, George K., 1974-1979 (Box 69, Folder 1)
          - Bendetsen, Karl R., 1976 (Folder 2)
          - Bowman, George, 1975-1976 (Folder 3)
          - Braden, Spruille, 1967-1978 (Folder 4)
          - Decker, Fred (Univ. Prof. for Academic Order), 1976-1977 (Folder 5)
          - Hosmer, Craig, 1976 (Folder 6)
          - Jarrell, Albert E., 1967-1976 (Folder 7)
          - Kitchel, Denison, 1974-1976 (Folder 8)
          - Lee, Fitzhugh, 1977-1979 (Folder 9)
          - Loeb, William, 1975-1976 (Folder 10)
          - McBirnie, W.S. (Center for American Research and Education), 1967-1977 (Folder 11)
          - McIntire, Carl, 1975 (Folder 12)
          - Reagan, Ronald, Includes correspondence with Gordon P. Smith, Philip M. Battaglia, Michael Deaver, Jack B. Lindsey and Peter Hannaford. Also includes notes and a clipping relating to Dr. Dozer's interaction with Ronald Reagan, 1967-1977. (Folder 13)
          - Ryan, Paul B., 1975 (Folder 14)
          - Sabin, L.S., 1975-1978 (Folder 15)
          - Schlafly, Phyllis, 1972-1977 (Folder 16)
          - Settle, T.G.W., 1967-1976 (Folder 17)
          - Sharp, U.S. Grant, 1976 (Folder 18)
          - State Department (Henry Kissinger), 1968-1976 (Folder 19)
          - Thatcher, Maurice H., 1966-1972 (Folder 20)
          - Thomson, Meldrim, Jr., 1975-1977 (Folder 21)
          - Wagoner, Raymond, 1966-1971 (Folder 22)
          - Wallace, George C., 1973 (Folder 23)
          - Wayne, John, Predominantly letters to others, including a statement, 1977-1978. (Folder 24)
          - Zumwalt, Elmo R., Jr., 1976 (Folder 25)
        - Legal materials, Relates to efforts to block the negotiations and resultant treaties by legal methods, 1972-1979.
          - General. Legal documents, court transcripts, and fragments relating to the cases of Helms vs. Kissinger, et al. and Drummond vs. Bunker et al. SEE ALSO: Interest groups/Canal Zonians/PCZNPIC/Legal materials (Folder 26)
          - Correspondence (Folder 27)
        - Notes and lists. Primarily Congressional voting records (Folder 28)
        - Speeches and writings
          - General
            - General, Letters, pamphlets and flyers produced by the Committee, 1976-1978. (Box 70, Folder 1-3)
            - Fragments (Folder 4)
            - Letters to editors, Includes fragments, typescripts, holographs and clippings, 1972-1978. (Folder 5)
          - Collier, William B. (Folder 6)
            - General, Miscellaneous letters, notes and fragments, relating predominantly to writings, but also includes drafts of letters to Edward Teller, and California Attorney General E.J. Younger, 1973-1976.
            - Untitled
            - "Canal Treaty Revisions Contrary to Law," Includes draft letter, undated
            - "Nuclear Explosives Hold Up Long-Needed Improvement in Panama Canal," Original typescript; includes letters, 1969-1970.
            - "Panama Canal Modernization Geared to World-Trade Needs," Carbon typescript, undated
            - "Panama Canal Treaty Negotiations," Typescript draft, undated
            - "Torrijos Demands Nationalization of Canal Zone in New Treaty," Three typescript drafts, undated
          - Dozer, Donald M. Printed references to Dr. Dozer, For Dr. Dozer's writings on this issue, SEE: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS FILE, 1977-1978. (Folder 7)
          - DuVal, Miles P.
            - General
              - General. Biographical material, notes, correspondence, pamphlet, memorandum, clippings, 1946-1979 (Folder 8)
              - Fragments, 1976 (Folder 9)
            - "Interoceanic Canal Navigational Criteria - Discussion," Mimeographed copy, undated (Folder 10)
            - Cadiz to Cathay. Mimeographed excerpt, circa 1947
            - "The Marine Operating Problems, Panama Canal, and the Solution," Papers of the American Society of Civil Engineers. Mimeograph of printed article. A variation of this article was given as a presentation before the General Board of Consultants, Panama Canal, 1947 february 1947 May 13.
            - "The Big Ditch," Reprint, 1955.
            - "Memorial to the Congress,", 1970
            - "Memorial to the Congress, Panama Canal: Sovereignty and Modernization", Mimeographed copies, 1971, 1973, 1975. (Folder 11)
            - "Panama Canal Question: A Challenge to the Congress," Printed copy, 1977.
            - Review of David McCullough, The Path Between the Seas: The Creation of the Panama Canal, 1870-1914," Mimeographed copy, 1977.
            - "Panama Canal Treaty Implementation: Present Status," Mimeographed transcript, 1978.
            - "Panama Canal Surrender: A Calamitous Support for Soviet Imperialism," Mimeographed copy, 1978 June 10.
            - "William Crawford Gorgas--An Appreciation," Printed copy, 1978 october
            - "Panama Canal: The Story of a Book and the Consequences," Includes later variation. Mimeographed speech transcripts, 1978-1979.
            - "Monroe Doctrine: Its Universalization as Doctrine of the World," Mimeographed copy, 1980 May.
      - N.O.S.I. ("Not One Square Inch") (Ralph Winkler).
        - General. Press releases, mimeographed clippings, memoranda, letters to editors, resolutions, flyers, articles of incoporation, lists of members, 1976-1978 (Folder 12)
        - Correspondence, Includes letters to the American Legion, Ronald Reagan, President Ford, Congress, and ECSCZ, 1977-1979. (Folder 13-15)
      - Save the Panama Canal Club (Arthur Denchfield)
        - General. Business cards, newsletters, clippings, flyers, speech transcripts, cartoons, statements (Box 71, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence
          - General. Includes letters to the PCZNPIC, Griffin Bell, and Ronald Reagan, 1974-1979 (Folder 2)
          - Emergency Committee to Save the U.S. Canal Zone (ECSCZ), 1974-1976 (Folder 3)
          - Internal (Folder 4)
          - U.S. Congress, 1974-1979 (Folder 5-6)
          - Letters to editors, 1973-1979 (Folder 7)
    - Executive organizations
      - Defense Department, Correspondence, memoranda, and statement by Deputy Secretary of Defence William E. Clements, Jr., 1975-1977. (Folder 8)
      - State Department
        - General
          - General
            - General, Relates to the controversy over Robert M. Sayre's behavior as U.S. Ambassador to Panama, while trying to mediate between U.S. narcotics officials, the State Department and the Panamanian government. Correspondence, statements, telegram. Includes letters from Jesse Helms and John Murphy and transcript of Ambassador Sayre's testimony at confirmation hearing, 1972-1978. (Folder 9)
            - Non-printed material, Press releases, newsletters, wire reports, reports, memoranda, minutes of 107th meeting between the Panamanian Commissioners and the State Department, 1970-1979. (Folder 10)
          - Correspondence
            - General, 1969-1977 (Folder 11)
            - U.S. Congress, Includes two letters from S. Morey Bell, Deputy U.S. Negotiator, 1967-1976. (Folder 12)
          - Reports (Folder 13)
            - Background Notes, "Republic of Panama", 1970 december
            - Edwin S. Costrell, "U.S. Policy Toward Panama, 1903-Present: Questions of Recognition and Diplomatic Relations and Instances of U.S. Intervention", 1974 April 22.
            - "Panama Canal Treaty Negotiations", 1977 january
            - "The New Panama Canal Agreement", 1977 august 17
            - 1977 september
              - "Texts of Treaties Relating to the Panama Canal"
              - "Documents Associated with the Panama Canal Treaties"
              - "The Meaning of the New Panama Canal Treaties"
        - Bunker, Ellsworth. Statements and speeches. SEE ALSO: Interest groups/U.S. Congress/H.R./Merchant Marine and Fisheries Committee hearings, 1977 november 30 (Folder 14)
          - Statement at the special meeting of the OAS, 1964 january 31.
          - "Panama and the United States: A Design for Partnership", 1974 March 19.
          - "Panama and the United States: Toward a New Relationship", 1975 May 22.
          - "The Panama Canal: Popular Myths and Political Realities", 1975 december 2.
        - Kissinger, Henry. Statements and speeches (Folder 15)
          - "The United States and Latin America: The New Opportunity", 1975 March 1.
          - "FY 1977 Security Assistance Program", 1976 March 26.
        - Linowitz, Sol. Speeches and statements (also includes some miscellany) (Folder 16)
          - Summary of remarks given at the Department of State, 1977 May 18.
          - "Why a New Panama Canal Treaty?", 1977 august 19.
          - "The Panama Canal Treaties--in the National Interest", 1977 october 18.
      - White House
        - Carter, James E. Form letters, memoranda and letters to Congress, wire report, letters to the ECSCZ, 1977 (Folder 17)
        - Ford, Gerald R. Includes material from his terms as a Congressman. Form letters, newsletter, letters. Includes original correspondence between Gerald Ford and Donald Dozer, 1967-1977 (Folder 18)
        - Johnson, Lyndon B. Printed and mimeographed statements, 1963-1966 (Folder 19)
        - Nixon, Richard M. Mimeographed letters to individual Congresspersons (includes transcript of speech by U.N. Ambassador John Scali to the Security Council meeting in Panama, letters from the ECSCZ, mimeographed press release entitled, "United States Foreign Policy for the 1970's: Shaping a Durable Peace," and a printed speech entitled "America's Role in the World,", 1973 March 20), 1969-1973 (Folder 20)
    - Latin Americans
      - General. Includes material from other Latin American countries as well as material generated by Latin Americans in the United States
        - Non-printed material
          - General, Wire reports, articles, letter from Pedro Ibanez Ojeda (Chile) to Spruille Braden, 1969-1977. (Box 72, Folder 1)
          - Organization of American States. Resolutions and the Act of the Special Session, 1964 february 4 (Folder 2)
        - Printed material, Clippings and mimeographed articles. Includes two statements by Carlos Andres Perez, 1971-1978. (Folder 3)
      - Panamanians
        - General
          - Non-printed materials
            - General, Wire reports, radio broadcast transcript, letter, itinerary, flyer. Includes text of 1903 Panamanian declaration of independence, 1903-1976. (Folder 4)
            - OAS documents, Two speech transcripts by Miguel J. Moreno, Jr. (Panamanian Ambassador to the OAS), and draft resolution, 1964 january-february (Folder 5)
          - Printed materials
            - General, Primarily Panamanian newspaper clippings; also includes other miscellaneous mimeographed clippings, a report by La Estrella de Panama, "Panama Makes Known its Reasons to Reject the 1967 Treaty Projects," and a letter to Rep. Daniel Flood from Panamanians working in the Canal Zone, 1963-1977. 1970, 1971 (Folder 6)
            - Panamanian Mission to the United Nations, Update...Panama. Series of five packets containing various reports and articles, 1977 (Folder 7)
        - Reports
          - Panamanian Committee for Human Rights, Vol. 1 (General) and Vol. 3 ("Panamanian Economy Under the Torrijos Regime), 1976 (Folder 8)
          - Republic of Panama, "Teleological Position of the Restoration Movement of " (S), parts I and II, 1968, October 11, 1968 (Folder 9)
        - Speeches and writings
          - Arguizola, Gustave, "Violation of Human Rights and Civil Liberties in Panama," and a mimeographed transcript of response to President Carter's speech of, circa 1977, 1978 february 1 (Folder 10)
          - Arias, Arnulfo. Mimeographed transcript of speech given upon return from exile, 1978 June 10 (Folder 11)
          - Eleta, Fernando A., Diogenes de la Rosa, Ricardo M. Arias, Roberto R. Aleman, and Guillermo Chapman, relating to Treaties Evaluation Commission, 1970 september 5 (Folder 12)
          - Escobar Bethancourt, Romulo, "Canal Neutrality Keeps Panama from Being a War Theatre," and "Negotiations Before the Eyes of the People," undated Mimeographed copies, 1977 august 20 (Folder 13)
          - Gonzalez Revilla, Nicolas. Speech to Panamanian Assembly, and statement before the General Assembly of American States, Mimeographed copies; latter includes cover letter from Jorge E. Illueca, 1977 august 19 1977 June 15. (Folder 14)
          - Illueca, Jorge. Mimeographed copy of speech, 1972 december 13 (Folder 15)
          - People's Party. Ruben Dario Sousa, "Developments in Panama," and an interview in New Times, a manifesto, Cesar de Leon, "United States Seeks to Mediatize the Revolutionary Process in Panama," and a speech by Sr. Castellanos at 23rd Congress of the Communist Party, Moscow, "Message of the People's Party of Panama in Connection with the Carter-Torrijos Treaty. Mimeographed copies, 1966 March-April, 1966-1977 (Folder 16)
          - Royo, Aristides. Mimeographed copy of letter to President Carter, 1980 january (Folder 17)
          - Socialist Revolutionary Faction. Mimeographed copy of statement, documents relating to canal negotiations, and resolutions, 1975 september 5 (Folder 18)
          - Tack, Juan Antonio, Mimeographed copies of a speech, a letter to the editor, and an interview, 1970-1975. (Folder 19)
          - Torrijos Herrera, Omar. Newspaper interviews, letters to Gerald Ford and Edward Kennedy, flyers, Clippings and mimeographed copies, 1970-1977. (Folder 20)
    - Military organizations. NOTE: Materials relating to the Defense Department are located under Interest groups/Executive/Defense Department
      - General
        - General, Flyers, pamphlets, press releases, book promotional material, printed article, miscellany, resolutions, 1971-1978. (Box 73, Folder 1)
        - Correspondence
          - General, Miscellaneous letters between military groups and to the ECSCZ. Includes letters from Thomas H. Moorer, Thomas Lane, Barry Ryan, and other individual officers, 1967-1977. (Folder 2)
          - Executive, Letters from John S. McCain, Jr. and a collective group of retired admirals, 1975-1977. (Folder 3)
          - U.S. Congress, Includes letters from Fitzhugh Lee, L.S. Sabin (includes short article), and others, 1973-1978. (Folder 4)
        - Letters to the editor, 1975-1976 (Folder 5)
        - Speeches and writings (SEE ALSO: Interest groups/U.S.Congress/ Senate and H.R./Committees
          - General, Articles from serials, particularly Proceedings of the U.S. Naval Institute. Includes articles by Paul B. Ryan, V.P. McDonald, Hanson W. Baldwin, G.V. Underwood, J.D. Hittle, J.K. Singlaub, Bruce C. Clarke, George S. Brown, 1958-1980. (Folder 6-7)
          - Eaker, Ira C. (Lt. Gen.), Press release and letter to Rep. Daniel Flood (annotated). Mimeographed copies, 1971-1979. (Folder 8)
          - Lane, Thomas A., Miscellaneous statements, printed article, 1971-1975. (Folder 9)
          - Schildhauer, C.H., "The Problem of a New Canal: The Best Solution," Printed copy, includes press release, and correspondence with Dr. Dozer, 1966 May 21. (Folder 10)
          - Settle, Thomas G.W., Mimeographed and holograph statements, 1975-1978. (Folder 11)
          - Van Natta, Thomas F., III. Mimeographed speech transcript, undated (Folder 12)
          - Willenbucher, Franz O., Letters to the editor, obituary and speech transcript entitled "Panama Canal: Catalyst for Restoration of National Will". Includes letters to the ECSCZ, 1967-1976. (Folder 13)
      - American Legion
        - General, Letters to congresspersons, wire service report, memoranda, pamphlet, press releases, speech transcript, printed article, 1968-1979. (Folder 14)
        - Correspondence (Folder 15)
          - General, Letters to the ECSCZ, internal memoranda, form letter, press release, reports and printed article, 1966-1979.
          - Executive, 1970-1977
          - U.S. Congress, 1971-1978
        - Newsletters, 1976-1979 (Folder 16-17)
        - Resolutions, 1966-1979 (Folder 18)
      - Military Order of the World Wars
        - General, Form letter, memoranda, newsletters, resolutions, and correspondence with ECSCZ, 1967-1978. (Folder 19)
        - Serial issues (Officer Review), 1976-1978 (Folder 20)
      - Naval Reserve Assocation. Report and open letter to Congress, 1978 (Box 74, Folder 1)
      - Retired Naval Personnel, Newsletter, 1974-1975 (Folder 2)
      - Veterans Affiliated Council, Letters and resolutions, 1973. (Folder 3)
      - Veterans of Foreign Wars. Newsletters (American Security Reporter), resolutions, letters to congresspersons, 1968-1977 (Folder 4)
    - U.S. Congress
      - General
        - General
          - Non-printed material. Lists, legal briefs, flyer, legislative history reference materials (includes legal and administrative codes) (Folder 5)
          - Printed material. Congressional Record, 1912-1978 (Folder 6-9)
        - Reference material
          - General, Reports, acts, laws, regulations, transcripts. Tangentially related to the Panama Canal issue, 1845-1974. (Folder 10)
          - Legal codes relating to Panama, 1950-1962 (Folder 11)
        - Reports
          - General. Miscellaneous printed reports, 1968-1975 (Folder 12)
          - Atlantic-Pacific Interoceanic Canal Study Commission. Annual reports, (#2-#5). Includes notes, memorandum, comment by Rep. Flood, and cover letters from Presidents Johnson and Nixon to Congress, 1966-1969 (Folder 13-14)
        - Resolutions received from state legislatures (Folder 15)
          - Arkansas, 1977 July 8
          - California, circa 1967-1977
          - Indiana, 1975 July 7
          - Oklahoma. Includes cover letter to Rep. Flood, 1969
          - Virginia. SEE: U.S. Congress/Senate/ General/Committees/Judiciary/ Statements/Canada, A. Joseph
      - House of Representatives
        - General
          - General
            - General. Lists, form letters, press releases, newsletters, and other letters from Congresspersons. Includes correspondence with the ECSCZ (Box 75, Folder 1)
            - Bills, 1965-1979 (Folder 2)
            - Resolutions, 1966-1977 (Folder 3)
          - Committees
            - General
              - General. Letters from collective groups and ad hoc committees, 1969-1975 (Folder 4)
              - House Republican Research Committee. Report, 1975 July (Folder 5)
              - Republican Committee on Western Alliances. Report and press release, 1967 June-august
              - Republican Study Committee, "The Panama Canal Treaty?", 1977 Sept 16
            - Foreign Affairs (Folder 6)